Guide to the Yonekazu Satoda Papers, Photographs, and Films
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Yonekazu Satoda papers, photographs, and moving films
1941-1948
WA MSS S-2897
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.7
(11 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
This collection includes papers, photographs, and moving films that document the internment of Japanese American Yonekazu Satoda at the Jerome Relocation Center in Arkansas, 1942-1945, as well as his military service with the United States Army in Japan, 1946-1948. Additional material documents other aspects of his life, especially his education as an accountant, as well as correspondence with friends and businesses.
Satoda, Yonekazu, 1921-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Vigilante Rare Documents on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 11 (moving film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Yonekazu Satoda (born 1921)
Yonekazu "Yone" Satoda was born in Hanford, California in 1921, a son of Otokichi "Fred" Satoda (1885-1968), originally from Hiroshima, Japan, who immigrated to the United States in 1902, and Asano Satoda (1894-1990), who immigrated to the United States from Japan in 1920. He had two siblings, Fumiye Satoda (later Yeabisu) (born 1922) and Masaharu Satoda (born 1924).
Satoda graduated from University of California in 1942, the same year that authorities sent him to the Jerome Relocation Center in Denison, Arkansas. In February 1945, the United States Army drafted Satoda. He received basic training at Camp Hood, Texas, and attended Officer Candidate School at the Infantry School at Fort Benning, Georgia, as well as Military Intelligence Service Language School at Fort Snelling, Minnesota. From November 1946 to August 1948, Satoda served as a first lieutenant and military intelligence officer in Tokyo and Hokkaido, Japan. After discharge from the active duty, Satoda served in the United States Army Reserves from 1949 to 1969; he retired as a major.
In March 1961, Satoda married Taka "Daisy" Uyeda (born circa 1928) and they had three children. Satoda worked as an accountant and lived in San Francisco, California.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes papers, photographs, and moving films that document the internment of Japanese American Yonekazu Satoda at the Jerome Relocation Center in Denison, Arkansas, 1942-1945, as well as his military service with the United States Army in Japan, 1946-1948. Additional material documents other aspects of his life, especially his education as an accountant, as well as correspondence with friends and businesses.
Material related to his internment at the Jerome Relocation Center includes a diary he kept from May 1942 to February 1945, as well as photographs that document the camp and his family.
Material related to his military service includes training information from Officer Candidate School at the Infantry School at Fort Benning, Georgia, as well as photographs and moving films created during his service in Japan.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Papers, 1941-1948. II. Photographs and Moving Films, circa 1942-1948.
Concentration camps -- Arkansas; Concentration camps -- Arkansas -- Pictorial works; Japanese American soldiers; Japanese American soldiers -- Pictorial works; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945 -- Pictorial works; World War, 1939-1945 -- Concentration camps -- Arkansas; World War, 1939-1945 -- Concentration camps -- Arkansas -- Pictorial works; World War, 1939-1945 -- Japanese Americans; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, Japanese American; Arkansas -- Pictorial works; Japan -- Pictorial works; Japan -- History -- Allied occupation, 1945-1952 -- Pictorial works; Diaries; Motion pictures (visual works); Negatives (photographic); Photographic prints; Satoda, Yonekazu, 1921-; Infantry School (U.S.); Jerome Relocation Center (Ark.); Jerome Relocation Center (Ark.) -- Pictorial works; United States. Army -- Officers -- Pictorial works
- Papers, 1941-1948; Series I; 1; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into six subseries: Personal Papers, School Papers, United States Army Material, Outgoing Correspondence, Incoming Correspondence, and Ephemera
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of papers created and collected by Satoda.
  - Personal Papers
    - Diary, 1942 May 12-1945 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notes on personal expenditures, 1944 July -November (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - United States Income Tax Return forms, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pocket notebook, circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Deposit slips, 1947 March 26-1948 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Money order receipts, 1947 July 3-1948 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Receipt for traveler's checks, 1948 August 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Receipt for a driver's license, 1948 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - School Papers
    Arranged chronologically
    - University of California, Final exam schedule, 1941 December (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - University of California, Syllabus for a course in family relations, syllabus, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - LaSalle Extension University, Problems in Practical Accounting, course material, circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
    - [No folder], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - United States Army Material
    - M. V. Patton, "Prohibition Against Casting Articles from Moving Trains", 1943 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Information on Village Fighting", 1944 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - United States War Department. Troop Train Commander's Guide. Washington, D.C.: United States Government Printing Office, 1944 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Position Sketching", 1944 November (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Company Administration: Supply", 1944 November (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Infantry-Engineer Teamwork in the Attack of a River Line", 1945 February 15
      Related Archival Materials note
      Stored in Box 12 (Broadside)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Company Administration: Morning Reports", 1945 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Tactics: Rifle Company in the Night Attack", 1945 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Court-Martial Procedure", 1945 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Explosive Reference Sheet", 1945 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - United States Army Infantry School, Pocket reference card for strength of company sections, command and service units, infantry regiment, 1945 April 1; 2 cards (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Company Administration: Unit Funds", 1945 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Hygiene and Sanitation", 1945 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Tactics: Combat Orders", circa 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Tactics: The Heavy Weapons Company in Attack, Terrain Exercise", 1945 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Form for a Brief Estimate of the Situation", 1945 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Technique of Rifle Fire Range Estimation", 1945 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Military Intelligence Section, Interrogation Vocabulary, circa 1945 June (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Tactics: Rifle Company in the Attack", 1945 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - United States Army Infantry School, Sample military correspondence, 1945 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Actions and Mental Procedure of Squad Leader when he has a Job to do," pocket reference card, 1945 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Classified Documents", 1945 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Leadership", 1945 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Steps in Small Unit Troop Landing," pocket reference card, 1945 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "Preparation of an Exercise: Sand Table", 1945 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - United States Army Infantry School, "A Guide for the Preparation of an Exercise," pocket reference card, 1945 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Military Intelligence Service Language School, Special Orders Number 95, 1946 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - United States Army Infantry School, Officers' Record of Leave Granted, 1946 April 8-1947 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Satoda, Yonekazu. Schedule of classes for the interrogation team of the 356th Communications Reconnaissance Company in Hakodate, Hokkaido, 1947 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Material related to an official reprimand for allowing men under his command to give gifts to Japanese nationals, 1947 June 18-July 9 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - 357th Headquarters Intelligence Detachment, Athletic Program, circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Includes scrap paper made from maps of the Okayama Prefecture of Japan
    - Russian language worksheets, circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Military insignias
      - Insignia for the rank of First Lieutenant in the United States Army, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Blank military identification tag, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    Carbon copies of outgoing correspondence
    - AutoBridge Company, 1947 December 11 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Bank of America, 1947 January 27-August 13 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - California Alumni Association, 1947 November 20-1948 February 29 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Civilian Merchant Marine Committee, 1948 June 16 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - LaSalle Extension University, 1947 January 27-July 11 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Pavelle Color Incorporated, 1948 March 18 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Photo Surplus Sales, 1948 June 2 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Royaltone Camera Stores, New York City, 1948 March 14-18 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - United States Department of the Treasury, 1947 February 7 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - University of California, Berkeley. Associated Students Bookstore, 1947 August 26 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1944-1948
    - Akimoto, Ted, 1948 June 11- August 27 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Art Center School (Los Angeles, California), 1948 August 27 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Brooks Institute of Photography, 1948 September 10 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - California Alumni Association, 1948 March 23 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Columbia University, 1948 August 25 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Dalton, John, 1948 December 21 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Davidson & Licht Jewelry Company, 1948 February 21 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Eijima, W., 1948 December 24 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Fred Archer School of Photography, circa 1948 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Fujita, Roy, 1948 December 10 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Fujiwara, Shizu, 1948 December 24 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Golden Gate College, San Francisco, California, 1948 September 21-October 1 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Healds Business College, 1948 August 16 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Kawahara, Effie, 1948 August 14 (Box 3, Folder 73)
      Also includes a letter from his brother-in-law, Tak
    - LaSalle Extension University, 1943 August 14-1947 February 12 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - L.C. Smith & Corona Typewriters, 1947 November 24-25 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Los Angeles Institute of Applied Photographic Arts, 1948 September 14 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Mai/Nick, 1948 May 1-December 16 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Matsumara, Joyce Y., 1948 June 9 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Mori, M., 1948 August 31-December 21 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Morikani, George?, 1948 March 8 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Movie-of-the-Month-Club, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Nagatani family, 1944 March 7 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Omachi, Henry Takashi, 1948 February 16-December 21 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Omatsu, George, 1948 December 18 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Pellish, Alex, 1948 August 18-November 26 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Pittsburg Photo Supply, 1948 August 4 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Robertson, Pat, 1948 January 14-December 20 (Box 3, Folder 87)
      Biographical/Historical note
      Wife of William O. Patterson
    - Reserve Officers Association of the United States, 1948 July 23 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Royaltone Camera Stores, 1948 March 30 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Schmit, Winnie and Dick, 1948 December 22 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Takemato, Takeo, 1948 December 17? (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Teri?, 1948 December 22 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Tojo, Jim, 1948 August 1-16 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Tokumato, Kim, 1948 December 21 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Tom, 1948 December 22 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - United States Veterans Administration, 1948 August 27 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - United States War Department, Finance Office, United States Army, 1947 March 4-April25 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - University of California, 1948 August 23-September 9 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - White, Fay Thomas, Sr., 1948 December 20 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Wilshire School of Photography, 1948 September 2 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Woodbury College, Los Angeles, California, 1948 August 25 (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Worsham, G. O., 1948 June 8 (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Orphaned envelopes
      - Ajima, H., 1948 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 103)
      - Brown Photo Company, undated (Box 3, Folder 104)
      - Photo Surplus Sales, 1948 June 18 (Box 3, Folder 105)
      - Stanford University, undated (Box 3, Folder 106)
      - United States Veterans Administration, 1948 August 24 (Box 3, Folder 107)
      - United States War Department, undated (Box 3, Folder 108)
      - Unidentified, 1948 December 21 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Ephemera
    - War Relocation Authority, Instructions to Evacuees on Seasonal Work Leave, circa 1943 (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - National Geographic Society and James M. Darley. The World Map: For the National Geographic Magazine. Washington, D.C.: Cartographic Department, National Geographic Magazine, 1943
      Stored in Box 13 (Broadside)
    - [No folder] (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Traffic Map of Hokkaido, circa 1947
      Stored in Box 14 (Broadside)
    - Clippings of photographs from the San Francisco Chronicle newspaper: Chuck Hanger playing basketball for University of California, as well as the marriage of Lieutenant Colonel William R. Cameron and Alison Stilwell, 1947 December 24, 29 (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - Business cards of chiefly Japanese officials and businesspersons, circa 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - Castle Films, undated (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - Da-Lite Screen Company, undated (Box 3, Folder 115)
    - Movie-Mite Corporation, undated (Box 3, Folder 116)
- Photographs and Moving Films, circa 1942-1948; Series II; 2.7; (8 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
  Series I is organized into three subseries: Photographic Prints, Negatives, Photographic Material Housing, and Moving Films.
  This series consists of photographs and moving film created and collected by Satoda, as well as examples of photographic material housing. This includes nearly 100 photographic prints, circa 700 photographic negatives, and four moving films, as well as examples of unprocessed and unexposed negatives and moving film.
  - Photographic Prints
    - Hollywood Nite Club Photos, Informal portrait of an Asian American woman at the Persian Room, Hotel Sir Francis Drake, San Francisco, California, circa 1948 (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Calmus, Kaye, for the United States Army Signal Corps, Photographs of a performance of the opera Carmen at the Imperial Theatre in Tokyo, Japan, for military occupation personnel, 1947 December 23; 5 photographic prints (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Worsham, G. O., for the United States Army Signal Corps, Photographs of the Japanese Repatriation Project, 1948 May 13; 18 photographic prints (Box 4, Folder 119)
      Images from aboard the freighter Shinko Maru that document the repatriation of Japanese nationals from Maoka, Karafuto (Kholmsk, Sakhalin), which the Soviet Union acquired during World War II, to Hakodate, Hokkaido
    - Picture postcards of Sarasota, Florida, undated; 6 postcards (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Unidentified photographic prints, undated; 64 photographic prints (Box 4, Folder 121-129)
  - Negatives
    - Jerome War Relocation Center, circa 1942-1945; 24 photographic negatives (Box 5, Folder 130-153)
      Originally housed in an envelope addressed from the Optometry Clinic at the Jerome Relocation Center in Denison, Arkansas, to the Riggs Optical Company in Little Rock, Arkansas
    - Japan
      - Hiroshima, circa 1946-1948; 70 photographic negatives (Box 5, Folder 154-213)
      - Matsumae, Hokkaido, circa 1946-1948; 9 photographic negatives (Box 5, Folder 214-218)
      - Mount Hakodate, circa 1946-1948; 10 photographic negatives (Box 5, Folder 219-224)
      - Nikkō, Tochigi, circa 1946-1948; 30 photographic negatives (Box 5, Folder 225-236)
      - Nikkō, Tochigi; and Hakodate, Hokkaido, circa 1946-1948; 11 photographic negatives (Box 5, Folder 237-242)
      - Ōnuma, circa 1946-1948; 2 photographic negatives (Box 5, Folder 243-244)
      - Tokyo, circa 1946-1948; 14 photographic negatives (Box 5, Folder 245-258)
      - Yokohama, circa 1946-1948; 12 photographic negatives (Box 5, Folder 259-265)
    - Unidentified photographic negatives from an accompanying storage album, undated; 50 photographic negatives (Box 6, Folder 266-315)
    - Unidentified photographic negatives, undated; 90 photographic negatives (Box 6, Folder 316-405)
    - Unidentified photographic negatives, undated; 105 photographic negatives (Box 7, Folder 406-508)
    - Unidentified photographic negatives, undated; 165 photographic negatives (Box 8, Folder 509-668)
    - Unidentified photographic negatives, undated; 106 photographic negatives (Box 9, Folder 669-681)
    - Exposed and unprocessed 120 millimeter color film rolls, circa 1948; 2 rolls of film (Box 10, Folder 682)
    - Unexposed 120 millimeter black-and-white film rolls, circa 1948; 8 rolls of film (Box 10, Folder 683)
  - Photographic Material Housing
    - Fuji Photo Film Company, "Dayyot" photographic negative sleeves, circa 1946-1948 (Box 10, Folder 684)
    - Marui-Imai Department Store, Photographic negative sleeves, circa 1946-1948 (Box 10, Folder 685)
    - Mevi, Photographic negative albums, undated (Box 10, Folder 686)
  - Moving Films
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Unidentified moving film, undated; 16 mm black-and-white film (Box 11, Folder 687)
    - Unidentified moving film, undated; 16 mm black-and-white film (Box 11, Folder 688)
    - Unidentified moving film, undated; 16 mm color film (Box 11, Folder 689)
    - Unidentified moving film, undated; 16 mm color film (Box 11, Folder 690)
    - Cine-Kodak moving film magazine, undated; 16 mm unexposed color film (Box 11, Folder 691)
- Oversize
  - United States Army Infantry School, "Infantry-Engineer Teamwork in the Attack of a River Line", 1945 February 15 (Box 12 (Broadside))
  - National Geographic Society and James M. Darley. The World Map: For the National Geographic Magazine. Washington, D.C.: Cartographic Department, National Geographic Magazine, 1943 (Box 13 (Broadside))
  - Traffic Map of Hokkaido, circa 1947 (Box 14 (Broadside))